<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"/usr/share/sgml/docbook/dtd/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % included SYSTEM "included.ent">
%included;
]>
<chapter id="generalities">
  <title>Generalities about &ocaml-name; packages in Debian</title>
  
  <section id="name-ocaml">
    <title>The name of the game</title>
    
    <para>
      The correct name of the language is
      <emphasis>&ocaml-name;</emphasis>. Other
      spellings/capitalizations like <quote>Objective Caml</quote>, <quote>ocaml</quote>,
      <quote>OCAML</quote>, <quote>O'Caml</quote> should be avoided
      when talking about the OCaml project, the system, or
      the programing language.
    </para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="bytecode-native">
    <title>Bytecode and native code</title>
    
    <para>
      The OCaml compilers can produce two kinds of executables:
      bytecode and native. Native executables are usual ELF executables
      produced for a particular CPU architecture, while pure bytecode
      executables are written in a language which can only be run on a
      OCaml bytecode interpreter. A pure bytecode executable starts with a
      magic string invoking the interpreter, so that bytecode
      executables can just be invoked like native executables. There are also
      <quote>custom</quote> bytecode executables, which embed a bytecode program along
      with a bytecode interpreter; these files are ELF executables. OCaml
      compilers to native code are not provided for every
      architecture.  On a Debian system, the list of architectures for
      which the currently installed version of the OCaml system
      provides compilation to native code can be found in the file
      <filename>/usr/lib/ocaml/native-archs</filename>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Native executables are in general faster to execute than
      bytecode executables since they are compiled specifically for an
      architecture. Bytecode executables are smaller than native code
      executables. If considering only one process the advantage in
      size is annihilated by the need for the OCaml runtime system
      for executing bytecode, however there is an advantage when
      running several bytecode processes in parallel since the runtime
      system can then be shared.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Pure bytecode executables have the advantage of being portable, which
      means that a pure bytecode executable can usually be run without having to be
      recompiled on any architecture for which an OCaml bytecode
      interpreter is available. For Debian, this has the advantage
      that packages containing only bytecode executables have
      <code>Architecture=all</code>, which reduces archive space and
      auto-builder load.  It also reduces download and installation
      size for users in case they install several bytecode packages.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      An important decision to take when building a Debian package is
      whether to support bytecode, native code, or both. We aim to
      support development both of bytecode and native code
      applications, hence libraries should be distributed both in
      bytecode and native code (see the <ulink url="#libpack">section on
      library packaging</ulink>). For packages containing executables,
      the rule is:
      
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para> If the execution of the program requires a
	lot of CPU power then the executables in the package should be
	compiled to native code on architectures where this is
	possible, and to bytecode elsewhere.  Typical examples are
	coq, or edos-distcheck. See the <ulink
	url="#native-prog">section on native code
	packages</ulink>.</para></listitem>
	
	<listitem><para> If the execution of the program is very fast
	on typical application cases then the program contained in the
	package should be compiled to bytecode. Typical examples are
	hevea, or headache. See the <ulink
	url="#bytecode-prog">section on bytecode
	packages</ulink>.</para></listitem>
	
	<listitem><para> Only in special cases, for instance when both
	versions provide different features, should a package contain
	programs both compiled to bytecode and native code.  See the
	<ulink url="#bytecode-native-prog">section on combined
	bytecode and native code packages</ulink>. </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="compiler-overview">
    <title>Overview of the OCaml compilers</title>
    
    <section id="byte-native-compilers">
      <title>Bytecode and native code compilers</title>
      
      <para>
	The <package>ocaml-native-compilers</package> package contains
	the OCaml compiler executables built in native mode:
	<command>ocamlc.opt</command>, which produces bytecode, and
	<command>ocamlopt.opt</command>, which produces native
	code. Since the OCaml compilers are themselves written in
	OCaml this package exists only on architectures where
	compilation to native code is supported.
      </para>

      <para>
	The <package>ocaml-nox</package> package contains the OCaml
	compiler executables built in bytecode mode:
	<command>ocamlc</command>, which produces bytecode, and on
	architectures where compilation to native code is supported
	the compiler <command>ocamlopt</command>, which produces
	native code. It is important to understand that on
	architectures where compilation to native code is supported
	<emphasis>both</emphasis> packages contain compilers from
	OCaml to both bytecode and native code, the difference lies in
	the nature (installation size and execution speed) of the
	compiler executables.
      </para>
      
      <table>
        <title>OCaml compilers</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <thead>
           <row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry>Compiles to bytecode</entry>
              <entry>Compiles to native code</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Compiler executable in bytecode</entry>
              <entry><command>ocamlc</command></entry>
              <entry><command>ocamlopt</command></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Compiler executable in native code</entry>
              <entry><command>ocamlc.opt</command></entry>
              <entry><command>ocamlopt.opt</command></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>
	See <xref linkend="bytecode-native"/> on a discussion whether
	to produce native code or bytecode. 
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="files">
      <title>Files used and produced by the OCaml compilers</title>
      
      <para>
	The &ocaml-name; toolchain can produce or use the following kind of files:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      pure bytecode executables (they can be recognized since they start
	      with the shebang line <code>#!/usr/bin/ocamlrun</code>)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      bytecode executables linked in <emphasis>custom
	      mode</emphasis>.  They are generated by
	      <command>ocamlc</command> when the
	      <option>-custom</option> flag is given at link
	      time. Those executables are in ELF format and include
	      both the final bytecode and the bytecode
	      interpreter. The <command>strip</command> command should never
	      be invoked on them since it will remove the bytecode
	      part.  Bytecode executables linked in custom mode are
	      depreciated and should be avoided.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>native executables (in ELF format)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>bytecode libraries (<filename>*.cma, *.a</filename>)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>native libraries (<filename>*.cmxa</filename>)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      shared libraries (for C bindings) (<filename>dll*.so</filename>,
	      <filename>lib*.so</filename>)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      static libraries (for C bindings) (<filename>lib*.a</filename>)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>bytecode object files (<filename>*.cmo</filename>)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>native object files (<filename>*.cmx, *.o</filename>)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>native plugin object files (<filename>*.cmxs</filename>)</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      configuration files for handling libraries with &ocamlfind;
	      (<filename>META</filename>)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Building packages using OCaml</title>

    <section>
      <title>Findlib and ocamlfind</title>

      <para>&ocaml-force; has chosen to fully support the
      <application>findlib</application> library. This is a suite of
      tools and libraries that help to manage OCaml libraries. This software is not
      specific to Debian and works on all platforms where OCaml is
      available. Through the years, this has become the de facto standard 
      when relying on external libraries. The main frontend is called
      &ocamlfind; and provided by the package <package>ocaml-findlib</package>.
      </para>

      <para>Even though compiling OCaml projects in Debian is still possible
        without &ocamlfind; it is highly recommended to use it.
      </para>
    </section>
        
    <section>
      <title>The OCaml system in Debian</title>

      <para id="package-type">
      There are three categories of OCaml packages in Debian:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Development packages contain OCaml objects required
            for the development or compilation of OCaml programs, or
            specifically for the creation of Debian packages
            containing OCaml programs.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Runtime packages contain OCaml objects necessary to run
            compiled programs. A runtime package is always associated
            with a development package.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Simple binary packages contain everything that does
            not fall into the two former categories. This includes
            bytecode and native executable of application programs,
            documentation, etc.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
      The <package>ocaml</package> package depends on all the basic
      packages needed to develop programs with OCaml. More
      specifically, the packaging of OCaml is split into smaller
      packages. The packages with suffix <package>-nox</package>
      contain libraries that do not need the X Window system (i.e.,
      for programs that don't use the <code>Graphics</code>
      module).  Here is the list of binary
      packages into which the OCaml system is organized:
  
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>
            The <package>ocaml</package> and <package>ocaml-nox</package>
            packages contain the compiler and its libraries. They can be
            both considered as development packages.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          The <package>ocaml-native-compilers</package> package
          contains the OCaml compilers built in native mode
          (<command>ocamlc.opt</command> and
          <command>ocamlopt.opt</command>).
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
            The compilers themselves are built in native mode,
            nonetheless, both compilers for compiling toward bytecode
            and native code are contained in this package.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              The <package>ocaml-base</package> and
              <package>ocaml-base-nox</package> packages contain the
              interpreter and runtime libraries needed by bytecode
              programs compiled with OCaml (in particular, the package
              <package>ocaml-base-nox</package> contains the
              <package>ocamlrun</package> program). They can both be
              considered as runtime packages associated to
              <package>ocaml</package>, resp.
              <package>ocaml-nox</package>.
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
              <package>ocaml-base-nox</package> contains also OCaml
              interface objects <filename>*.cmi</filename>, which are
              normally only in development packages because they are needed to
              run the <command>ocaml</command> toplevel from the package
              <package>ocaml-interp</package>.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <package>ocaml-interp</package> package contains the
            toplevel system for OCaml (<package>ocaml</package>) which
            provides for an interactive interpreter of the language.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <package>ocaml-mode</package> package contains the
            OCaml Emacs mode. This is the original Emacs mode provided
            with the OCaml upstream distribution, not to be confused
            with the tuareg Emacs mode which is in the package
            <package>tuareg-mode</package>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <package>ocaml-source</package> package contains the
            sources of the OCaml compiler.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <package>ocaml-compiler-libs</package> package contains
            some internal libraries of the OCaml compiler (needed only in
            very rare cases, e.g. for developing languages which reuse
            OCaml internals).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      Since libraries produced by OCaml are binary incompatible when
      compiled with different releases of OCaml, versioned virtual
      packages are also provided by packages at items (1), (2), (6)
      and (7): <package>ocaml-&ocaml-version;</package>,
      <package>ocaml-nox-&ocaml-version;</package>, etc.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="general:build-dependencies">
    <title>Choosing the right build dependencies</title>
    
    <para>
      Compiling with native code versions of the compilers is generally faster
      than with compilers in bytecode. Unfortunately, the
      <package>ocaml-native-compilers</package> package is not available on
      every architecture. <emphasis>Packages should therefore never depend
      directly on this package.</emphasis> In order to build big programs and
      benefit from this natively built compiler, packages should depend on
      <package>ocaml-best-compilers</package> which itself depends on
      <package>ocaml-native-compilers</package> where available and on
      <package>ocaml</package> elsewhere. Since it is a virtual package, it
      cannot be a versioned dependency. The version dependency should thus be
      carried by the <package>ocaml</package> dependency. Note that dependency
      on <package>ocaml-best-compilers</package> is only necessary for really big
      programs for which compilation takes a lot of resources. For most small
      programs the compilers from the <package>ocaml-nox</package> package are
      perfectly sufficient, and faster to install in a build environment than
      compiler executables in native code.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="general:dependencies">
    <title>Putting the right binary dependencies</title>

    <para>
      Bytecode is specific to an upstream version of the OCaml
      system. Therefore, any package containing bytecode has to depend
      directly or indirectly on the packages providing the OCaml
      runtime system in precisely the version for which it was
      compiled (for instance,
      <package>ocaml-base-&ocaml-version;</package>.) This is in
      particular the case for bytecode programs, but it is also the
      case for native code programs on the architectures on which
      there is no native code OCaml compiler, and on which the program
      will be actually compiled to bytecode (see the <ulink
      url="#native-prog">section on packaging native code
      programs</ulink>). The exact dependencies of libraries packages
      are discussed in the <ulink url="#libpack">chapter on library
      packaging</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
      In order for a package to be easily rebuild, or even binNMUed,
      in case of a transition from one OCaml version to another, these
      dependencies must not be hardcoded in
      <filename>debian/control</filename>. Instead, substitution
      variables must be used which are instantiated from the
      <filename>debian/rules</filename> file. See the discussion on
      build systems in the Debian OCaml Developers Reference for a
      discussion how this can be achieved.
    </para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="dh-ocaml">
    <title>Dh_ocaml</title>
    <para>&ocaml-force; has created a system to compute dependencies
    between &ocaml-name; packages and to ensure type-safe linking.  It
    requires to use new substitution variables in
    <filename>debian/control</filename>:
    </para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Use the <code>${ocaml:Depends}</code> substitution variable
	in the field <code>Depends</code>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add a field <code>Provides: ${ocaml:Provides}</code> in
        development and runtime packages.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      More detailed information about this work can be found <ulink
      url="http://upsilon.cc/~zack/stuff/ocaml-debian-deps.pdf">here</ulink>.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Integrating OCaml packages in Debian</title>
  
  <section>
    <title>Location of OCaml directories</title>
    <para>
      The root of all installed OCaml libraries is the
      <emphasis>OCaml standard library directory</emphasis>, which
	is &ocaml-sys-dir;. This location can be obtained from the
	OCaml compiler by invoking it as <userinput>ocamlc
	-where</userinput>.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="archive-section">
      <title>Debian archive section</title>
      <para>
	Packages intended for the development of OCaml programs or
	packages, as well as packages necessary for the execution of
	OCaml code (like runtime systems or libraries) should have
	their section set to <code>ocaml</code>.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	End user applications that are not specifically aiming at
	OCaml development or execution support but just happen to be
	implemented in OCaml should have their section set according
	to their application domain (<code>games</code>,
	<code>science</code>, etc.). General development tools that are
	not specific to OCaml development go into section
	<code>devel</code> (example: headache).
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="doc-base">
      <title>Documentation</title>
      <para>
	Documentation relevant to programming in OCaml should be
	registered with doc-base in Section
	<code>Programming/OCaml</code>. This is the case for API
	documentation generated using &ocamldoc;. See the <ulink
	url="#documentation">section on generating
	documentation</ulink>.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
