<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"/usr/share/sgml/docbook/dtd/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % included SYSTEM "included.ent">
%included;
]>
<chapter id="progpack">
  <title>Packaging OCaml programs</title>
  
  <section>
    <title>Creating packages for OCaml programs</title>
    
    <para>
      The source package should, if possible, use the name of the upstream
      package without modifications.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Packages containing executables (as opposed to libraries) may be
      produced by compiling to bytecode, native code, or both. See
      <ulink url="#bytecode-native">this discussion of which mode to
      choose</ulink>.
    </para>
    
    
    <para>
      Package containing only bytecode executable, native executable or data 
      are simple binary package, as explained <ulink url="#package-type">
      previously</ulink>.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="bytecode-prog">
    <title>Bytecode packages</title>
    <para>
      A bytecode package has all its binaries compiled into
      bytecode. It depends on a package containing the OCaml runtime
      system. As a consequence, such a package has its architecture
      field set to <code>all</code>.
    </para>

    <para>
      All bytecode executables should be linked dynamically against
      the shared libraries for C bindings, to not bloat the
      archive. That said, upstream authors often favor statically
      linked bytecode executables (&ocamlc; option
      <option>-custom</option>), because in this case they don't need
      to worry about the presence of the dll stub libraries.  This is
      not a valid reason to use statically linked bytecode in a Debian
      package where package dependencies can fix this problem.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      A bytecode package must depend on the runtime package
      that is required to run it. Typically, it should depend on
      &ocaml-base-nox-vpkg; (or &ocaml-base-vpkg;, if if the program
      uses the <code>Graphics</code> module).
      It can also depends on the virtual
      <package>libXXX-ocaml-byte-ABCD</package> provided by the
      runtime package <package>libXXX-ocaml</package> (see <ulink
      url="#general:dependencies">the section on binary
      dependencies</ulink>).
    </para>
    
    <para>
      A bytecode package must build-depend-indep on &ocaml-nox-pkg; (or
      &ocaml-pkg; if the program uses the <code>Graphics</code> module).
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Bytecode programs which are compiled by <userinput>ocamlc
      -custom</userinput> must not be stripped. In particular, their
      package should be excluded from the <command>dh_strip</command>
      script. When compiled this way, an ELF executable is generated
      containing the ocaml interpreter, and the bytecode of the
      program in a section which is removed when the program is
      stripped.  For more information, see the bug <ulink
      url="http://bugs.debian.org/256900">256900</ulink>. <emphasis>Custom
      bytecode executable is a deprecated feature of OCaml -- for now
      they still exist but should be avoided</emphasis>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Bytecode programs should not be compiled for debugging,
      i.e. they should not be compiled using the <option>-g</option>
      option to &ocamlc;.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="native-prog">
    <title>Native versions of programs</title>
    <para>
      Native OCaml compilers are not available on all
      architecures. For architectures missing native compiler, a
      bytecode version of the program should be provided.  Native code
      packages are specific to an architecture, that is they have
      <code>Architecture=any</code> in the source package.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The <filename>debian/rules</filename> file should build the native
      code executable if supported on the architecture it is built on,
      and fall back to building the bytecode version if no working
      native code compiler is available. As a consequence, the rules of
      <xref linkend="bytecode-prog"/> also apply here.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      It is safe to consider that detection of native architecture means
      availability of &ocamlopt; or <command>ocamlopt.opt</command> when 
      building.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="bytecode-native-prog">
    <title>Bytecode and native versions of programs</title>
    <para>
      This should be done only under exceptional circumstances.
      Packages providing both native and bytecode versions of a
      program <command>prog</command> usually name them respectively
      <command>prog.opt</command> and <command>prog.byte</command> and
      provide a symbolic link <command>prog</command> to the best
      available version (generally <command>prog.opt</command>).
      Please consult the rules of <xref linkend="bytecode-prog"/>
      and  <xref linkend="native-prog"/>.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
